<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A salutation in the love of God and in the fellowship of the work of His blessed truth ... with a word of exhortation and counsel ... also a warning unto all them that have long known the truth but have not, neither obey it with all their hearts ... / by Samuel Cater.</title>
            <author>Cater, Samuel, d. 1711.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1672</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31341</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1489</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36283</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15626268</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15626268</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104256</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31341)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104256)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1183:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A salutation in the love of God and in the fellowship of the work of His blessed truth ... with a word of exhortation and counsel ... also a warning unto all them that have long known the truth but have not, neither obey it with all their hearts ... / by Samuel Cater.</title>
                  <author>Cater, Samuel, d. 1711.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1672.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Pastoral letters and charges.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:104256:1"/>
            <p>A SALUTATION IN THE Love of God, AND In the Fellowſhip of the work of his bleſſed Truth, unto all the Faithful Brethren and Siſters in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord, who are Begotten by the Immortal Word of God unto a lively Hope, which liveth and abideth for ever.</p>
            <p>With A Word of <hi>Exhortation</hi> and <hi>Counſel</hi> unto all whoſe Faces are ſet
<hi>Sion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> and who have found the <hi>Narrow-Way that leads to Life,</hi> whoſe hearts are tender of Gods Glory, and deſire to walk therein.</p>
            <p>Alſo a <hi>Warning</hi> unto all them that have long known the Truth, but have not, neither do obey it with all their hearts, that they may Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem the time that yet remaines, and prize the Day of their Viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and while they have the Light, walk in it, leſt utter Darkneſs come upon them, and the Door of Mercy be ſhut.</p>
            <p>By <hi>SAMUEL CATER.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1672.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:104256:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:104256:2"/>
            <head>A Salutation In the <hi>Love of God,</hi> and in the <hi>Fellowſhip</hi> of the work of his bleſſed <hi>Truth,</hi> unto all the Faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful <hi>Brethren</hi> and <hi>Siſters</hi> in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Friends, Brethren and Siſters,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHom God, through the riches of his Grace, and breakings of his bleſſed Light into our hearts, hath thereby gathered us out of the dark world, which lyeth in wickedneſs, amongſt whom we had our converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in times paſt, in which time we were Ignorant of the knowledg of the true God, and ſtrangers unto eternall Life, which by his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Grace and heavenly Light he hath now brought us unto the knowledge of, to the great Satisfaction of our hearts and comfort of our ſoules, which peace and ſatisfaction the world could never give us, neither can they now take it away from us, bleſſed be the name of the Lord our God, who ſpeaks peace to his children, and none can ſpeake trouble, but in his holy will we reſt under the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of his winges, where none of the inſtruments of cruelty can make us afraid; for the Seed is known, which is ſatisfied in the will of God, and can, and doth obey and follow the Lord as faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully in adverſity as in proſperity, whereby we are fully ſatisfied thorow the work that God hath wrought in us by his unchangable truth and ſpirit, that the day of his power is come, in which day he hath made us willing to deny our own wills, and to obey the will of the Lord God our maker, and to take up the croſs whereby ſelfe is daily crucified, and to follow Chriſt Jeſus, and to keep the word of his patience, whereby we are made pertakers of the fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ious promiſes, who keeps and delivers his in the hour of temptation; who ſaith to the Seed of <hi>Jacob, Call upon me in the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:104256:3"/> time of trouble, I will hear and deliver thee, and thou ſhalt glorifie me.</hi> And now dear Brethren, often hath the Lord made us Eie-witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and pertakers of this his love and mercy, who hath preſerved our feet from falling; yea and hath delivered us out of many troubles: and when we have ſeen none to help, then hath he been a preſent help unto us, both outwardly and inwardly. So that the Lord hath not been wanting unto us, bleſſed be his holy name, who hath, and doth hand forth his mercy as largly now to them that fear him, as he did unto the generations that are gone before us. Oh! the love of our God and how large it doth abound to us-ward, even unto them that fear him, ſo that I can ſay as the Prophet ſaid. <hi>Truly the Lord is good to Iſrael even unto ſuch as are of an upright heart:</hi> For Dear Friends, who is their that can ſay they want any good thing, that put their truſt in the Lord, and are given up to ſerve and obey him with all their hearts? So that our ſouls can ſay to the glory of our God, <hi>That Wiſdom, and grace, nor any good thing doth the Lord withhold from them that obey him with an upright heart; for in him all fullneſs dwels; who feeds the hungry with good things, and covers the naked with the garment of Salvation, and beautifies his Elect with high praiſes; the poor he maketh rich with durable riches and everlaſting righteouſneſs; ſo that he raiſes the poor beggar from the dunghill of the worlds glory, and ſets him in heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly places in Chriſt Jeſus, where his ſoul feeds quietly in the freſh paſtures of love and life, and drinks at the Fountain of living water, which becomes as a well ſpringing up in his ſoul to Life Eternall; the lame alſo doth the Lord, in this the day of his bleſſed power which he hath made us pertakers off, make to walke; thorow the virtue of his love he refreſhes the ſoules and hearts of all them that wait upon him, whereby their ſtrength is daily renewed, to run the wayes of his holy commandments, which the Lord makes eaſie to all them that are of an upright heart, the tongue of the dumb he looſed, through the vertue of his Life, and ſhowering down his bleſſed dews of heaven into their thirſty Soules, which cauſeth them to publiſh his praiſe, and to ſet forth his glory: So that we ſee his Promiſe fulfilled; in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, waters breake forth, and ſtreams in the deſart, and the place of barrenneſs is now become fruitful, whereby praiſes is brought forth to the glory of the Lord our God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that his preſence is with us as certainly now, as ever it was with his Children in any Age who obeyed his holy will, and ſtood
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:104256:3"/> in his councel; who for their obedience to the Law of their God, were ſometimes caſt into the Lions den, ſomtimes into the fire, ſometimes impriſoned, and others their goods ſpoyled, and the Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ds preſence was with them, who upheld them, and cauſed them to ſing praiſes unto His name, in the feeling of His holy Power which they injoyed when their bodies were lockt in the Priſon, and their feet in the Stocks.</p>
            <p>Even ſo now, He is known unto us that have believed in His name, by the virtue of His love, for He deals His bread of Life which is His fleſh unto our Souls, by the virtue of which our Souls live and receive ſtrength to praiſe the Living God our maker; and the miſterys of Life and Godlineſs hath the Lord made known unto us, who hath cleanſed us, and purged us by His blood, and waſhed and Regenerated us by His holy Word: So that there is a Remnant, that can and do read in Gods bleſſed Light the miſteryes of Life, and theſe can ſay, <hi>The bread which we break is the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the body of Chriſt, and the cup which we drink is the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the blood of Chriſt:</hi> For although we be many members, and many miles diſtant, outwardly ſeparated one from another, and have ſundry gifts which God hath given us by His holy Spirit, which He hath ſent into our hearts, by the which we are led and guided to exerciſe the ſame, <hi>For the edifying of the body in the love of God, which conſtraineth us ſo to do, by which Spirit we are all baptized into the one body, and made partakers of the one bread which came down from heaven,</hi> by the which we are fed and nouriſhed, <hi>led and guided into all truth;</hi> In the ſence of which Mercy, and in the fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of this great Miſtery which is hid in Chriſt from all that are high and proud, and wiſe in their own conceit, and envious, and ſlight the Grace of God, <hi>Who reſiſteth the proud, but gives more Grace to the humble;</hi> I ſay, In the fellowſhip of this ever bleſſed and truly worthy, for ever to be loved and obeyed, Truth and Grace of God, which ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h done this bleſſed work for us; and hath made known this Miſtery of Life in us, the Salutation of my Life, in the unſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>akable Love and Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cy of our God is unto you all.</p>
            <p>Dear Brethren and Friends, whom the Lord hath made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers with me, and I with you, of this pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tious Faith, even the Faith which was of old delivered unto the Saints; which give us victory over the World, and by wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch we receive power to deny
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:104256:4"/> our ſelves and to do the will of our God, by which we feel a hope begotten in us which is as an Anchor moſt ſure and ſtedfaſt in our hearts, and ſouls, <hi>That nothing that is preſent, nor nothing that is yet to come, ſhall ever be able to ſeparate us from the love of our God;</hi> Nor decline our minds, nor pervert our hearts from following the Lord, and obeying his bleſſed Truth and holy Spirit which hath effected this good work in our hearts, and hath done us thus much good, which our tongues are not able to ſet forth, ſo fully as our Souls pertake and injoy of the benefit, in the ſalvation of our Souls from death; who hath by the Arm of His bleſſed Power re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in and unto us, preſerved our feet from falling and our hearts from fainting, and hath delivered our eyes from tears, <hi>And now hath given us beauty for aſhes, and the Spirit of joy and gladneſs for the Spirit of heavineſs;</hi> So that the heart that hath been purged through the execution of the Lords Righteous Judgments, now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyces in the enjoyment of his Mercies.</p>
            <p>But this is not every ones ſtate nor condition, who are convinced of Gods bleſſed Truth, and who are turned to the Light and Word of faith within, for its now with us as it was with them that the Apoſtle writ to, who were in ſeveral ſtates and conditions; there were ſome that were ſtrong men of full age, whoſe ſences were tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly exerciſed in the word of God and Doctrine of the Apoſtles, and theſe were ſuch that the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>Had obeyed from the heart their Doctrine which they preached, by the which they were ſaved, made free from ſin, and become ſervants to God, their fruit unto holyneſs, and their end everlaſting peace:</hi> Theſe were acquianted with the miſterys of Life and Godlineſs, and he ſaid to them, <hi>The bread which we break, is the communion of the body of Chriſt, and the cup which we drink, is the communion of the blood of Chriſt;</hi> for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they were many members, yet but one body, of which Jeſus Chriſt was the head, who had true experience of the work of the Lord.</p>
            <p>And to ſome they ſpake and writ, which were young in the faith, and had but little experience in the knowledg of the work of the Lords bleſſed Truth, unto which they were turned, and in the which they had believed, and by the which he told them they ſhould be ſaved, if they continued to the end in faith and obedience.</p>
            <p>Alſo the Apoſtle wrote and ſpoke to ſuch as had the knowledge of the Truth, but did not continue in faithful obedience thereunto
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:104256:4"/> to the end of their race, that ſo they might thereby receive the Crowne of Life, who yet aboad in the form, but had loſt the virtue of the Life and power which once they felt and injoyed, and which all do injoy which continue faithful unto the Lord, whoſe virtue and power keeps them alwayes freſh and green, and living to God.</p>
            <p>And now dear Friends there is ſomething in my heart, as one that hath obtained mercy of the Lord, and according to the experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence which God hath given unto me of his Love and Mercy, and as I feel the Lord requires of me for the eaſing of my heart, and clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of my conſcience unto you, that have believed in the Truth; And firſt unto you whoſe hearts are tender of Gods glory, and that deſire to have your Portion with the Sanctified in Chriſt Jeſus; all keep low, and wait in Gods holy fear, for the fear of the Lord will keep your hearts tender of his glory, for unto them that fears the Lord he revealeth his ſecrets: And all keep to the pure holy Light of Jeſus Chriſt, unto the which you have been turned by the Meſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngers and Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt, whom God hath ſent in his name and power, now, as he did in dayes paſt, to turn People from Darkneſs to Light, and all that were faithful in walking in it came to be redeemed from Sathans power; and knew then, and do now the power of God which ſaves the Soul: Therefore <hi>Dear Friends,</hi> be watchful in the Light of Jeſus that ſhines in your hearts, that you may all be led by it in the way which leads unto Peace, He is given for a Leader, and whoſoever is led and guided by him that is come a Light into the world, and now ſhines in thy heart, He leads to Peace, and gathers into Reſt: For this is the path which the Juſt walked in, who travelled to God in all Ages, which the wicked and ungodly hates; the path of the Juſt is a ſhining Light which ſhines unto the perfect day: And all you that are entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this path, be faithful to God, and dilligent to walk in it, and bring your deeds unto it, that you may be found in well doing, for them are they that ſhall, and do come to injoy Immortallity and Eternal Life by Jeſus Chriſt, who continue in well doing: And Chriſt ſayes, <hi>He that does well cometh to the Light, and bringeth his deeds unto it.</hi> And the Apoſtle ſaid to them he wrote to in his day, <hi>That they had this ſure word of Prophecy, whereunto they did well to take heed, as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Light that ſhines in a dark place.</hi> This alſo is my Teſtimony with many Brethren, that all, that ever come to have Life everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing muſt walk in it, love it, and obey the teachings of it: And
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:104256:5"/> therefore do I commit you all unto it, that have recieved the knowledge of it as unto that which is able, and on that which the Lord has laid help, that is mighty to ſave to the utmoſt all that bowes to the apearance of it. And therefore let your eyes be to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it to wait upon God in it, even for the Grace that is to be brought in the Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt, for as thou waiteſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly in the Light, it will let thee ſee how it is with thee, and how far thou haſt been faithful unto God, and in what thou haſt not been faithful, and wherein thou haſt d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne well, thou art juſtified by it, and in what thou doeſt evill, thou art condemned by it; and ſo here thou comes to ſee the Scripture fulfilled, which ſaith, <hi>Tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and anguiſh on every ſoul that doth evill, but glory, honour and peace, to them that worketh good:</hi> And therefore <hi>Dear Friends,</hi> as you deſire to have peace with God, keep to the Word and Grace of God which appears within, and which calls for purity and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence out of a pure heart; for them which went before us, which did injoy peace, and which do now injoy the ſame, and comes to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſuch high privilledges, and pertake of ſo great promiſes as to be Saints in the Light; they are ſuch as did and do obey the Grace and Truth of God with all their hearts, whereby they come to be elected unto God through Sanctification of the Spirit, and obedience unto the Truth: So <hi>Dear Friends,</hi> You that have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the knowledg of the bleſſed Truth of God, which is Chriſt, <hi>The way, the Truth, Life and Light,</hi> whereby through the Mercy and Love of God unto your Souls, you are made pertakers of that which <hi>David</hi> prayed unto God for, Lord ſayes he, <hi>Send forth thy Light, and thy Truth, and it ſhall conduct us unto thy holy hill:</hi> and for that ſame end hath the Lord our God viſited you with his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Light, whereby he hath guided your feet into the way of peace, that you may travel therein unto his bleſſed and everlaſting Kingdome, that ſtands in Peace, Righteouſneſs, and Joy in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, into which nothing that defileth, or worketh Abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion can enter: And therefore <hi>Dear Friends,</hi> This is the word of exhortation which lives in my heart unto you that have believed, wait in it, and keep to the word of faith which purifies the heart and cleanſeth the conſcience, for it is the pure in heart that come to ſee God, and to pertake of the great and pretious promiſes of Life and Peace, even ſuch as walk in the Light, in which there is no occaſion of ſtumbling; for in it every ſnare that the enemy of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:104256:5"/> our Souls layes to take our feet, or to intangle our affections with any viſible thing or to draw down our minds into the earth, and to give us a ſight of the viſible and carnal things, which if the mind and heart cloſe with them, and ſo enters into the Temptation, it brings darkneſs over the heart, and death upon the Soul, <hi>for to be carnally minded brings death,</hi> but obedience to the Spirit of the Lord, <hi>brings life and peace:</hi> And therefore all live in the Spirit, and obey Chriſt the Power and Wiſdome of God, and look not out at your own weakneſs nor at any Temptation of the enemy of your Souls, either without or within, but all look up to Chriſt in whom your help is, <hi>Who is able to ſave to the utmoſt all that comes to God by him;</hi> and none to be diſcouraged becauſe of the frownes of the ungodly or the threatnings of the wicked, for they are but as the crakling of thorns under a pot with the Lord our God, whom we in Soul, Body, and Spirit, ſerve and worſhip, who hath ſet bounds for them, and they ſhall do no more unto us, then ſhall make to the glory of our God, and to the advantage of his Truth, and for the trial of our Faith that when our Patience is tried, we may come forth in our Teſtimony, <hi>as gold tried in the fire;</hi> and then bleſſed are all that wait in patience, and reſt contented with all the flock of Chriſt, until the Lord renders vengeance on them that trouble us. But thou <hi>Dear friend,</hi> who art given up, and reſolved in thy heart and ſoul to ſerve and obey the Lord thy God, what ever it coſt thee, and thou haſt honeſtly counted the coſt, and thou ſeeſt the Pearl to be more worth then all that thou canſt part withall for it, or ſuffer becauſe of thy obedience to it, be not thou diſcouraged at the appearance of the wicked one, whoſe work the Lord thy God by his bleſſed Light is a diſcovering unto thee, but rejoyce in that the Lord hath made him manifeſt, who hath <hi>Sat in the Temple of God, exalting himſelf above all that is called God, ſaying that he himſelf is God;</hi> and this is he that Rules Head, King and Prince, in all the Children of diſobedience, which are yet in darkneſs, and who now proclaime him their King and Potentate; And both Prieſt, and Profeſſor, and Prophane, ſtrike hands with him, ſaying, That they never can, nor ſhall be freed from ſin, on this ſide of the grave, and ſo make the death and coming of Chriſt of none effect, who came to ſave his People from their ſins, and to Redeem them from all unrighteouſneſs, who will bruiſe the ſerpents head, and overcome his power in thee, <hi>For unto him all power in heaven
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:104256:6"/> and earth is committed;</hi> and this is he you are to look unto and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live in, who is come a Light into your hearts, <hi>And to bind the ſtrong man and ſpoyl his goods, and caſt him out;</hi> who w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll certainly do it, for he is come into your hearts, that is greater then he that Rules in the world, but he does, and will ſtrive to keep his poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion as long as by any meanes and wiles, or cunning craftineſs he can: And therefore my <hi>Dear Friends,</hi> All watch to the Light, for in that you will ſee and know, <hi>His cunning craftineſs whereby he lies in wait to deceive;</hi> and whom he can no longer deceive but with the Light he is ſeen, and by the power of God his Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are denyed by the honeſt hearted, <hi>Then he accuſeth before the throne of God night and day:</hi> And this is he which tells you who are tender of Gods glory, and hunger and thirſt after Righteouſneſs, that you ſhall never overcome all your corruptions, which you ſee to be the foes of your own houſe, but all believe in the Light, <hi>Which is the power of God unto ſalvation, unto every one that believes,</hi> and you ſhall come to ſee this accuſer caſt down, and by the power of the Living God overcome, and your feet ſet, <hi>And your houſe built upon the Rock; Which the gates of hell cannot prevail againſt, nor the floods of the ungodly</hi> can never overflow, nor the ſtormes of the wicked, neither can nor ſhall overcome: <hi>For the Lord preſerves his people, and delivers them that put their truſt in him:</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, This is the word that is in my heart in the true ſence of Gods love unto your Souls, that are come to the Light of Chriſt which is the way of Life, end ſee it to be a narrow way, and the gate where by you muſt enter into Reſt is ſtraight; I ſay unto you wait upon God, and keep ſubject unto his Grace which appears unto you, for in that lies your help; for that is the ſame that ever it was unto the Travelers in dayes paſt: For when
<hi>Paul</hi> the ſervant of God, who was deeply exerciſed in his mind and troubled in his heart, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of his own weakneſs, and the ſtrength of Sa hans accuſations and temptations, under the ſence of which he cried unto the Lord for help, whoſe anſwer was to him, <hi>My grace is ſufficient, for my power is made perfect in weakneſs;</hi> by the which he did come to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs help and deliverance from the body of ſin and death, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n his Soul praiſed the living God; and then as he received of the Lord ſo he Preached to others, and committed them unto God, and to the word of his Grace, which ſayes he, <hi>Is able to ſave your ſouls, and to give you an inheritance with the Sanctified in Chriſt Jeſus;</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:104256:6"/> and he ſayes, <hi>That this Grace hath appeared to all,</hi> that ſo many as obey it are brought into the perfect way of holyneſs in Gods fear. Therefore all know your minds ſtayed in it, and your h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arts ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected unto it, that ſo you may come to witneſs Reſt by it, to the which I commit you as unto that which I am a living witneſs, for the Lord is able to ſave your Soules, and to ſet your hearts at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to ſerve and praiſe the living God; And all be dilligent to keep your Meetings, to wait upon God with them that meet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to worſhip the Lord out of a pure heart: And all wait in the Light, and labour to keep your hearts and minds ſtayed in, and with his bleſſed and holy Spirit of Truth, upon the living God, that ſo his bleſſed peace you may all feel abounding in your hearts more and more, to the comfort of your Soules, that ſo in the living feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Gods heavenly power, you may have fellowſhip together: And all take heed that the enemy of your Souls, <hi>That goeth about like a roaring Lion, ſeeking whom he may devour,</hi> does not betray your ſimple minds, in cauſing your minds to wander from the Truth, or to let thoughts to reſt in your hearts, which is the work of the enemy to bring in to trouble you, when you are waiting upon God; But all ſubmit unto God, and in his name and power Judge them out, and let them not have a place in your hearts, for if you do, they will hinder you from hearing the voice of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved of your Souls. And all take heed of deadneſs, and drouſineſs, and ſleeping in Meetings, for that is a great diſorder, and brings diſhonour to the holy name of God, that is concerned in and amongſt you, which all that loves the Lord ought to be tender of, and it is alſo a great and heavy burthen to the Souls of the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous which ſits with you, and are preſerved in a freſh and living ſence of the goodneſs of the Lord, and it is alſo a great diſhonour unto your ſelves, as you are men and women that profeſs to meet together, to worſhip God in Spirit and Truth; for I do ſay and know, That Gods witneſs in all your conſciences, who ever have felt the power of God, and known the worſhip of God, that is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in Spirit, that when, and whilſt at any time, that ſleepy drouſy Spirit, prevails over any, although you may be in the Meeting with them that does ſerve and worſhip God, you do not then worſhip him; but bur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hens the Juſt in your ſelves and in others, for the Word of the Lord which the Children of God hear and feel, is quick and powe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ful; and Chriſt who is in the mideſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:104256:7"/> of thoſe that meet in his name, is a quickening Spirit, whoſe Life quickens the mortal bodys, and refreſhes the Immortal Souls of all his little ones, that wait for his appearance. And therefore all wait in Gods pure fear, that you may be covered with the Spirit of the Lord, that ſo your nakedneſs may not appear which is the cauſe of ſhame.</p>
            <p>And unto you that have long been convinced of the Truth, and have not been faithful unto it, but are in the ſtate of them the Apoſtle ſpeakes of, <hi>Who for the time might have been teachers of others, but now you have need one ſhould teach you the firſt principles of true Religion;</hi> for you are they that have not been faithful to God, who have not truly, nor throughly forſaken dead works, but reſt in a convincement of the Truth, ſaying and confeſſing to that which doth ſhew you and all men ſin, and convinceth of the ſame, is the Truth of God, and there is no other, but do not ſo obey it, as to become conformable thereunto, but reſt in the knowledg of the will of God, but does not yeild obedience unto it, and have gotten into a form of Truth, but for want of obedience to the ſame, doth not come to witneſs the power of God to Rule in your hearts: <hi>Freinds,</hi> You are in the fooliſh Virgins ſtate which: Chriſt ſpeaks of, which have got the lamps, but have not the Life and Virtue of the Love of God dwelling in you, by the which the Soul is daily fed and nouriſhed; but even whileſt your tongues may be talking of God, your Souls are in leanneſs, and this comes upon you, becauſe your hearts ſtill luſteth after that which Gods. Spirit is againſt, which you ought to come out of, and to be clean ſeparated from; and here you keep an enemy in your own bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and harbours a <hi>Dalila</hi> in your own hearts, while you ſuffer any luſtful deſire to live in your hearts, that Gods Truth hath appointed to be ſlain and crucified, which you ought to bear the Croſs unto, for the want of which you cannot follow Chriſt, until you deny your ſelves, and take up the Croſs to your own wills, to whatſoever it be that it luſteth after; for our God is Pure, Holy, Juſt, and Righteous, who will and does render unto every man according to his Works; for although he let the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old have their luſtful minds ſatisfied yet for it he brought leanneſs of Soul upon them, which was a, juſt Judgment of God upon them, which before he fed with bread from heaven; even ſo doth he now: Bleſſed be his holy name ſaith
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:104256:7"/> my Soul, for now doth the Lord refreſh and feed with bread from heaven, which the world knowes not, nor the diſobedient pertake not of, for the Lord our God refreſhes, cloathes, and feeds, and miniſters Peace and Comfort unto thoſe who are zealous for his name, and obedient to his holy Truth: But the diſobedient doth and muſt dwell in a dry Land: Therefore you that have the knowledge of this ever bleſſed, and worthy to be obeyed Truth, and Grace of God, whith is given you for to lead and guide you, to the Kingdome of the Living God; Prize your time, and improve your Talent; For I teſtifie unto you, that there is a Prize put into your hands, and an oppertunity hath God afforded you to get ſtrength, <hi>Before you go hence and ſhall be ſeen no more;</hi> But if you ſpend this pretious time, that the Lord hath given you, <hi>To work out your Salvation,</hi> and <hi>to make your calling and election ſure,</hi> Then God will be juſt in the day when your Ruin comes upon you; And his ſervant, and ſervants, will be clear of your blood; And the Talent which is a meaſure of the Lords good Grace and Spirit, will be taken from you, and will be a ſwi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> witneſs againſt you: And therefore, whilſt you have time prize it, and whilſt you have Light walk in it, leaſt darkneſs ſo much overtake you, and the cloud of errour through your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual diſobedience to the Light, growes ſo thick upon you, as you cannot ſee the way to God; and then the enemy of your Souls takes you wholly captive again to do his will: And then the Scripture comes to be fulfilled upon you: <hi>The Dog is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned again to his old vomit; and the Sow that was waſhed to the wallowing in the mire;</hi> And then thou art fit neither for the land nor for the Dunghil, but to be trodden under foot of men; and then falls into that ſnare that <hi>David</hi> prayed to the Lord to be kept from, that he might never become a Scorn to fools that had no underſtanding; for all of you that have in any meaſure obeyed the word and Grace of God, you have known cleanſing by it, ſo far as you have obeyed it; which is able to ſave and to cleanſe throughly, all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m that abides in it, whereby the words of Chriſt comes to be fulfilled, <hi>If you abide in my word, then are you my diſciples indeed; and you ſhall know the Truth, and the Truth ſhall make you free.</hi> And as you tender the glory of God and the good of your own Souls, wait dilligently to hear what the Spirit ſaith in, and unto you, for that will deal juſtly and truly
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:104256:8"/> with every one, for it is the ſame that ever it was, which juſtifies them that obey the Truth, but condemns and reproves in what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they do evill; And this is the Spirit that all are now to hear and obey, which ſpeakes a word in ſeaſon to every ones condition; And therefore all wait to hear what it doth ſignifie unto you, whether it be Judgment or Mercy, for through Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Mercy comes to be known, for by Judgment, that comes to be overcome which is contrary to the Lord; and therefore bleſſed are they that wait upon the Lord in the way of his Judgments, until by Judgment, that be ſlain that is contrary to the Lord; that ſo you may come to ſee, <hi>Mercy and Truth to meet together, and Righteouſneſs and Peace imbrace each other,</hi> which is the deſire of my Soul, who am a true Freind to your Souls.</p>
            <p>This to be Read in the Aſſemblies of Gods People, in the fear of the Lord, in <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and elſe where this may come; as <hi>Friends</hi> may ſee a ſervice therein.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Written at <hi>Monroſſe</hi> Priſon in <hi>Scotland,</hi>
                  <date>the eleventh Moneth, 1671. when I was there a Priſoner for the Teſtimony Of the Truth.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Samuel Cater.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
